<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sheharyar Naseer]]></title>
  <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-03T00:44:12+05:00</updated>
  <id>http://sheharyarn.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sheharyar Naseer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ubuntu 13.10 in Parallels - CRTC 80 Error]]></title>
    <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/ubuntu-13-10-parallels-monitor-configuration-crtc-80/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T16:01:16+05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/ubuntu-13-10-parallels-monitor-configuration-crtc-80</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night I spent hours configuring Ubuntu and Installing Dependencies, programs and God-knows-what for a new Hobby Project of mine, <a href="http://pupil-labs.com/pupil/">Pupil</a>.</p>

<p>It was a clean installation of Ubuntu 13.10 in Parallels 9 on my new Macbook. I had invested too much time installing pupil, only to find that the display drivers or GTK or something had been corrupted. This was the second time I was booting ubuntu and had been slapped in the face by this:</p>

<!--more-->




<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Could not switch the Monitor Configuration
</span><span class='line'>could not set the configuration for CRTC 80</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>image</strong></p>

<p>I restarted it, but received the same error. The login screen was perfect, mind you; The error presented it self only after logging in. There was nothing else; No Icons, no Menu bar, no Unity. I googled for hours and tried everything I could; <a href="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=1835391">Using xrandr</a>, <a href="http://kb.parallels.com/en/114097">Editing xorg.conf</a>, <a href="http://www.parallels.com/support/desktop/troubleshooter-en_US">Running Parallels Troubleshooter</a> and so much more. In the end, I was somewhat able to restore my installation by reinstalling my Parallels Desktop Tools.</p>

<p>These are the exact steps I followed after logging in:</p>

<ol>
<li>Press <code>Control + Alt + F1</code></li>
<li>In the full-screen terminal, login with your credentials</li>
<li>In the Parallels Desktop Menu, select <em>Devices > CD/DVD 1 > Connect Image</em></li>
<li>In the new Finder dialog, browse to <em>Applications > Parallels Desktop > Contents > Resources > Tools > pri-tools-lin.iso</em></li>
<li>Now back in your terminal screen, type the following commands:</li>
</ol>


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>sudo mkdir /media/cdrom
</span><span class='line'>sudo mount /dev/sr0 /media/cdrom
</span><span class='line'><span class="nb">cd</span> /media/cdrom
</span><span class='line'>sudo ./install
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Parallels Tools&#8217; installation will begin. Go through the steps and complete the installation. After that, reboot using: <code>$ sudo reboot</code></p>

<p>If everything went fine, you would at least be able to see your desktop. In my case, there was no Unity Sidebar or the top Menu Bar; But it&rsquo;s still something. Maybe installing Gnome would help.</p>

<p><strong>Lesson:</strong> Make regular <em>Snapshots</em> of your OSes in Parallels</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tinkering With Dart]]></title>
    <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/tinkering-with-dart/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T10:06:06+05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/tinkering-with-dart</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, on a friend&rsquo;s recommendation, I checked out <a href="http://dartlang.org/">DART</a>. It&rsquo;s an interesting language backed by Google.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Opening Files From Finder Using Keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/macosx-opening-files-from-finder-using-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T10:05:00+05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/macosx-opening-files-from-finder-using-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a recent Mac convert so it was really weird for me when I realized that hitting the Return key in Finder renames the file instead of opening it. I&rsquo;ve spent the better part of my life using Windows and Linux and as you can imagine this was really frustrating for me (and still is).</p>

<p>After a bit of Googling, I found out that you can open selected files in Finder using the <code>⌘ + O</code> combination on your keyboard. I&rsquo;m still trying to find a way to modify this to the &lsquo;Return&rsquo; key to have a consistent <em>Keyboard experience</em> on all my PCs.</p>

<p>Anyways, digging my new Macbook Air. :D</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yet Another Octopress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/yet-another-octopress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T03:13:21+05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sheharyarn.github.io/blog/yet-another-octopress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No. This isn&rsquo;t another rant by a new Rubyist about how Ruby is so beautiful, open and awesome &amp; how <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> has liberated yet another slave of <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a>. I love Ruby, Rails, Octopress and other <em>Hip</em> Geeky things; but I love Wordpress too. Moving to Octopress is somthing I have been wanting to do for a long time. I wanted to have complete control over my writings. I wanted them to be as minimal as possible, both in terms of design and code.</p>

<p><strong>Let me stop you right there.</strong> Octopress is not for you. You&rsquo;ll have to write in Markdown, there&rsquo;s zero community support compared to wordpress, you have to write and deploy from possibly only one system and you&rsquo;ll have to get your hands dirty. Real Dirty. Getting hard? Well, I am. My condition is something like <a href="http://billpatrianakos.me/blog/2012/10/31/the-making-of-an-octopress-theme/">Bill Patrianakos</a> tells it:</p>

<blockquote><p>There’s something about static files, Markdown, Git repos, the terminal, and a text editor that turns me on.</p></blockquote>

<p>Octopress is really cool. This might be my first public post on the platform, but I&rsquo;ve been experimenting with Octopress for months on my local system. The Sass, the Liquid Engine and other fine grains of the platform made me fall in love. But the theme &ndash; It was overly complicated and too much used on the web. I wanted it to be a little different and hence I decided to launch an Octopress Blog only when I have made my own Octopress theme.</p>

<p>Thus born was <code>Sybtle</code>, an Octopress theme created from scratch and inspired by the <a href="https://svbtle.com">Svbtle</a> online writing platform. I might release it in the future, but for now if you want to use it, you&rsquo;ll have to go through the <a href="https://github.com/sheharyarn/sheharyarn.github.io">code</a> yourself and clean it up.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s enough rant for today.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
