<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Otp, | Sheharyar Naseer]]></title>
  <link href="https://sheharyar.me/blog/categories/otp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://sheharyar.me/"/>
  <updated>2018-02-10T04:52:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://sheharyar.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sheharyar Naseer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working With GenStage in Elixir]]></title>
    <link href="https://sheharyar.me/blog/working-with-genstage-elixir/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-03T18:20:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://sheharyar.me/blog/working-with-genstage-elixir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>GenServers are an amazing part of the OTP ecosystem, helping solve a lot of complicated tasks
easily in Elixir. But working with multiple sets of GenServers together and exchanging data
between them has always been a hassle. <a href="https://hexdocs.pm/elixir/GenEvent.html">GenEvent</a> solved these problems to some
extent, but it did not provide support for backpressure or concurrency. This is where
<a href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/gen_stage">GenStage</a> comes in.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Last year <a href="https://elixir-lang.org/blog/2016/07/14/announcing-genstage/">announced on the official Elixir blog</a>, GenStage is a new behaviour
in the OTP family, built on top of GenServers. It is described as:</p>

<blockquote><p>GenStage is a specification for exchanging events with back-pressure between Elixir
producers and consumers</p></blockquote>

<p>but that doesn&rsquo;t convey its full power. The name hides the real meaning; instead of simple
producers and consumers, imagine concurrent stages in a pipeline that takes an arbitrary
number of input events, perform some operations on them and send them to the next stage.
Each stage can consume and produce many events at once, with multiple instances of each
stage running at the same time. The producers can produce as many events as they want, and
the consumers can consume them according to their demand with ease, with the behavior
handling the bulk of the logic.</p>

<p>A simple use-case of GenStage would look like a straight-forward pipeline like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/4RvaWBU.png" alt="GenStage Simple Use-case" /></p>

<p>But that doesn&rsquo;t do it justice, instead you should think about each stage having many
concurrent instances like this:</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/ddCa8kP.png" alt="GenStage Concurrent Instances" /></p>

<p>This is possible due to another behavior shipped with the library, called <code>ConsumerSupervisor</code>.
ConsumerSupervisors allow, well, supervision of multiple consumers or producer-consumers
for better reliability and fault-tolerance. For code examples, I would suggest you check
out the project on <a href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/gen_stage">Github</a>, the excellent documentation on <a href="https://hexdocs.pm/gen_stage/GenStage.html">Hexdocs</a> or
the <a href="https://github.com/elixir-lang/flow">Flow</a> library (which is an amazing implementation of GenStage!). But there are
some things you should take care of when working with GenStages in Elixir (that I had to
learn the hard way):</p>

<ul>
<li>Don&rsquo;t excessively produce events when there is no demand</li>
<li>If a long-running producer yields zero events when there is consumer demand, you have to
explicitly retry producing events again. Otherwise, it would just stop. A common case where
this would happen is, integration with external message queues</li>
<li>Use <code>Supervisor</code> for simple pipelines, and <code>ConsumerSupervisor</code> when dealing with concurrent
instances of a GenStage</li>
<li>Try to define explicit demands for consumers</li>
<li>Start the stages in order, and immediately subscribe to the previous stage for <code>consumers</code>
and <code>producer_consumers</code>, preferably in the <code>init/1</code> callback</li>
<li>Maintining overall demand in a producers' internal state is a good idea</li>
</ul>


<p>Here are some other excellent posts on the topic:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://elixirschool.com/en/lessons/advanced/gen-stage/">Elixir School: GenStage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://engineering.spreedly.com/blog/how-do-i-genstage.html">How do I GenStage?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://alexgaribay.com/2017/04/25/using-genstage-for-a-batching-pipeline/">Using GenStage for Batch Processing</a></li>
<li><a href="http://tomasztomczyk.com/2017/01/17/genstage-for-processing-jobs.html">GenStage for Processing Jobs</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
