<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ecto | Sheharyar Naseer]]></title>
  <link href="https://sheharyar.me/blog/categories/ecto/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://sheharyar.me/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-08T02:44:21-04:00</updated>
  <id>https://sheharyar.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sheharyar Naseer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EctoRut - Simple Ecto Shortcuts to Make Your Life Easier]]></title>
    <link href="https://sheharyar.me/blog/ecto-rut-simple-model-shortcuts/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-05T07:31:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>https://sheharyar.me/blog/ecto-rut-simple-model-shortcuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months back, I published an Elixir package called <a href="https://github.com/sheharyarn/ecto_rut"><code>Ecto.Rut</code></a>.
Ecto.Rut lets you call <code>Ecto.Repo</code> methods directly on the Model itself instead
of passing your Model as an argument to each <code>Repo</code> method call.</p>

<p>While the project&rsquo;s Readme and <a href="https://hexdocs.pm/ecto_rut/Ecto.Rut.html">Documentation</a> are self-sufficient in
getting you started, I wanted to write about my motivation for creating the
package in the first place.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Quick Introduction</h2>

<p>Ecto.Rut is simply a wrapper around <code>Ecto.Repo</code>, so it can let you do awesome
things like this:</p>

<p>```elixir
Post.all</p>

<h1>instead of YourApp.Repo.all(Post)</h1>

<p>Post.get(2)</p>

<h1>instead of YourApp.Repo.get(Post, 2)</h1>

<p>Post.delete(5)</p>

<h1>instead of YourApp.Repo.delete(Post, 5)</h1>

<p>Post.insert(title: &ldquo;Awesome Post&rdquo;, slug: &ldquo;awesome-post&rdquo;, category_id: 3)</p>

<h1>instead of:</h1>

<h1>changeset = Post.changeset(%Post{}, %{title: &ldquo;Awesome Post&rdquo;, slug: &ldquo;awesome-post&rdquo;, category_id: 3})</h1>

<h1>YourApp.Repo.insert(changeset)</h1>

<h1>Well, you get the idea</h1>

<p>```</p>

<h2>Motivation</h2>

<p>As I improved my Elixir skills, I needed to be better familiar with <code>Macros</code> and
Metaprogramming in general (see my talk on <a href="/blog/talk-introduction-to-elixir/">Introduction to Elixir</a>),
and it all started with random experiments in Elixir Macros. At the same time,
working on my Phoenix applications, I grew tired of calling <code>Repo</code> methods for
even the simplest database queries on my models and missed the <em>Rails-y</em> way of
calling <code>Model.find</code>, <code>Model.update</code>, etc. I saw that (some) other developers
on the Elixir Forum felt the same way too.</p>

<p>I took this as an opportunity to publish my first Hex Package, while refining
my Elixir skills at the same time. The goal of the project here is to not to
fully replace <code>Ecto.Repo</code> calls in your app, but to reduce code repetition
and simplify and speed up development.</p>

<p>For complex queries, it&rsquo;s highly recommended that you use the original <code>Ecto.Repo</code>
calls and not this package.</p>

<h2>Implementation</h2>

<p>Ecto.Rut is implemented as a simple <code>behaviour</code> using Macros that can be activated
by calling the <code>use</code> construct. The basic structure of the code looks something
like this:</p>

<p>```elixir
defmodule Ecto.Rut do
  defmacro <strong>using</strong>(opts \ []) do</p>

<pre><code>quote bind_quoted: [opts: opts] do

  def all,              do: call(:all,    [@model])
  def get(id),          do: call(:get,    [@model, id])
  def delete(struct),   do: call(:delete, [struct])

  defp call(method, args \\ []) do
    apply(@repo, method, args)
  end

end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The gist above is just an example, not the <a href="https://github.com/sheharyarn/ecto_rut">full code</a>. But it does convey
how  powerful Macros in Elixir truly are. Abstraction over abstraction leads to
beautifully simple code without comprimising any of the performance and giving
rise to creative solutions at the same time.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have much else to say about the topic, but the beauty and flexibility of the
Elixir language keeps surprising me every now and then.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
